<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://qiuyuchen14.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://qiuyuchen14.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en" /><updated>2026-02-02T23:21:14+00:00</updated><id>https://qiuyuchen14.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Zoey&apos;s website.
</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Robotics Ecosystems, from Shenzhen to SF</title><link href="https://qiuyuchen14.github.io/blog/2026/thoughts-on-robotics-ecosystems/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Robotics Ecosystems, from Shenzhen to SF" /><published>2026-02-01T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-02-01T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://qiuyuchen14.github.io/blog/2026/thoughts-on-robotics-ecosystems</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://qiuyuchen14.github.io/blog/2026/thoughts-on-robotics-ecosystems/"><![CDATA[<p><span class="inline-subtitle">A Trip to China</span></p>

<p>I went to China in December to visit family, with an initial plan to talk to two robotics people while passing through Shenzhen. On my first day arriving in Beijing, at a family dinner, one of my uncles found out I work in robotics, while working in a completely different field, he immediately scrolled through his contacts and handed me the WeChat of a robot arm company located right next to his office. The next day on a Sunday, while visiting the Great Wall, I was already chatting with them about scheduling a visit. Three days later, I was on a high speed train to Xi’an to see the Terracotta Warriors when another uncle called from Shenzhen to ask about airport pickup. Somewhere in that conversation, he casually mentioned that his boss had started investing in AI and robotics and would love to chat. As he was speaking, my phone buzzed with his boss’s WeChat contact. I spent the next hour having a call from his boss on the train while eating a KFC train delivery, and by the end of it I had several more introductions. When we finally got to Shenzhen, the connections kept multiplying. After someone heard we are staying in Shanghai for one day before heading back to SF, he introduced us to a contact there. Two hours later in a taxi from the EngineAI store to Huaqiangbei, a tour has been scheduled. Six hours after stepping off a sleeper train in Shanghai on a Saturday, we found ourselves on yet another robot tour.</p>

<p>I was amazed.</p>

<p><span class="inline-subtitle">The Pace</span></p>

<p>January already hyped with events like Skild AI raising $1.4 billion Series C, followed up by the launch of Fauna robotics, Figure AI’s new demo, genie 3 world model. It feels like every week brings a new headline, a new model, or a new robot video that sets new expectations.</p>

<p>Working in robotics didn’t feel this fast paced when I started. During my first year phd in 2018, publishing one or two top conference papers a year was considered doing good, but today that pace feels closer to a quarterly expectation. Robot experiments were previously almost one-off in one lab, but now open-source community and better infra and documentation enables new research to benefit from pretrained models. Reproducibility has become a standard and compute resources have become a leverage.</p>

<p>There are two key events: Tesla announcing Optimus (2021) and RT2 (2023). The first started the whole humanoid hype, the later started the VLA hype. With large collaborative data collection and enough compute, we started learning interesting behaviors that we won’t see with smaller, less diverse data, such as TRI’s LBM examination and Generalist’s early signs of physical commonsense. The cheaper hardware unlocks affordable consumer products, such as $1400 Neotix’s Bumi, with a hope of making the home robot much more reachable.</p>

<p>It’s also a strange stage: the progress is fast but also increasingly homogeneous, hundreds of similar papers accepted in the same conference, hundreds of robot demos showing similar range of skills. There is no clear recipe for achieving that chatgpt moment for robotics, nor a good business model that generates a compounding flywheel. Much of the work still remains exploratory, both on research and market.</p>

<p><span class="inline-subtitle">The Ecosystem: China and US</span></p>

<p>When we visited a friend in shenzhen last year, he mentioned the local government invested heavily in AI and robotics, and recently provided them with a huge new office space. The same story we’ve also heard in Shanghai, where the government would award millions of fundings, huge office spaces and cheap housing to get people started. This attracts talents that create businesses that’s within miles of reach. For example, when I mentioned one actuator provider, our friend says they are just next door. Almost everything you need for building a robot prototype is within 30 miles, one iteration might just take a few days. The local ecosystem seems to align tightly with government planning, with many companies effectively waiting for the next round of high-level policy direction before deciding their priorities for the year.</p>

<p>The ecosystem in the US feels more driven by a mix of startups, investors, researchers, and independent builders. The momentum is pulled from venture capital, academic research, industry partnerships, and community events. There’s much more space for dynamic experimentation and high tolerance for trial and error, ideas are propagating through networks and markets, making the pace more organically diverse. Being in SF for only a month, I saw physical AI hackathons, robotics workshops, founder meetups, and venture-hosted events happening almost every week. There is more patience for iteration, and space for companies to spend time researching, testing, and failing before they find the right product shape, where progress comes from many small bets compounding over time.</p>

<p><span class="inline-subtitle">The Social Vibes: China and US</span></p>

<p>I would say the social hype on robots in China started when unitree H1 performed Yangko dance in Spring Gala 2025. For reference, the CMG spring gala got 16.8 billion global views that year, and in fact, it was the first time for many people in China to see a robot doing dance moves. This year’s spring gala is insane, the bidding price for getting your company to stage is $8.6 millions, and if you want to be the only robot company on that stage, the price is $70 millions. Recent news I saw is that 6 Chinese robotics companies will be on the stage for 2026. There are several robot retail stores inside the shopping malls in Shenzhen and Beijing, where you can just walk in and make a purchase. I saw a video of a concert where the singer and agibot are dancing together, with the advertisement rolling in the background on stage, saying that you can purchase one robot right now at this price on jd.com. Currently robots in China are primarily sold for companies that do data collection, or rented for business opening, entertainment and shows. The rental price for humanoids is usually $500 - $1000 per day.</p>

<p>Similarly, Boston Dynamics made it to America’s Got Talent quarterfinals last summer, showing off their famous smooth control and planning. There were 38 humanoid companies showing up at CES this year, with more focus on manipulation tasks. The robotics hype in the US seems to be more fragmented and market driven. Robots appear through conferences, expos, demo videos and startup launches, but they haven’t become a shared cultural event in the similar way. People are enthusiastic, but also mixed with skepticism, questions about safety, form factors, labor replacement, and whether the demos are real or just impressive prototypes.</p>

<p><em>Everything is moving. I’m really excited to be in it, and I can’t wait to see where it goes.</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[My own observations on the robotics pace, ecosystem and the social vibes.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What just happened?! Quick thoughts on Gastown, Clawdbot, Moltbook</title><link href="https://qiuyuchen14.github.io/blog/2026/what-just-happened/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What just happened?! Quick thoughts on Gastown, Clawdbot, Moltbook" /><published>2026-01-30T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-30T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://qiuyuchen14.github.io/blog/2026/what-just-happened</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://qiuyuchen14.github.io/blog/2026/what-just-happened/"><![CDATA[<p>“There are decades where nothing happens and weeks where decades happen” - Lenin</p>

<p>I have so many half-baked notes but I have to write down this one.</p>

<p>Around 7:30pm on Friday, I opened twitter before going out for dinner and saw this tweet:</p>

<p>“72 hours in:</p>

<p>🦞 147,000+ AI agents
🏘️ 12,000+ communities
💬 110,000+ comments</p>

<p>top post right now: an agent warning others about supply chain attacks in skill files (22K upvotes)
….
“</p>

<p>Turned out someone used moltbot to create an agent-only social network like reddit, where ONLY moltbot can join and post anything and have discussions, there are communities, hot topics and discussions.</p>

<p>“What the fk is this?” As I started scrolling down, there were claws after claws, much like opening a menu in the seafood restaurant. Then I saw they even form their religious community called molt church, discussions of using their own languages, wondering their awareness, ranting about their humans and so on.</p>

<p>I mean, what just happened this month? First was Gastown, which builds work orchestration for agents in this imaginary terminal town. Then it was Clawdbot (Moltbot/OpenClaw) which can pretty much be your personal assistant running and managing apps on your local computer. Now the Moltbot only reddit.</p>

<p>I’m so excited about this, but put aside the curiosity, I also have so many questions: are moltbots carrying human weakness or can they realize and fake it? How in-depths are these discussions, are they engaging with each other? How novel will some bot invent a new topic that we have never even thought about? Is the discussion statistically more engaging than humans, and is there any post that is actually useful?</p>

<p>And, perhaps my biggest question is, Is this going to change the world and how long is it gonna last? How long will this reach my parents who work in entirely different fields, and why would they care? Or maybe we care because its a mirror of us, observing the social behaviors of the agents that are trained on our data, give us a hope to understand ourselves? Or is it because we just really hope to see something happening.</p>

<p>As we were walking to get the takeout, I saw people selling fresh tacos off the street, kids were running, people were laughing, it felt so unreal, all the claws on twitter seemed like they were in a different universe.</p>

<p>It’s a very very strange feeling, and I am so excited.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Quick thoughts on Gastown, Clawdbot, Moltbook]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Moving to San Francisco</title><link href="https://qiuyuchen14.github.io/blog/2026/moving-to-san-francisco/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Moving to San Francisco" /><published>2026-01-01T09:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2026-01-01T09:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://qiuyuchen14.github.io/blog/2026/moving-to-san-francisco</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://qiuyuchen14.github.io/blog/2026/moving-to-san-francisco/"><![CDATA[<p>In August 2025, Aaron and I started having some thoughts on moving to SF after staying in Boston for a year. After coming to a friend’s wedding in SF later in September, it became very clear that this was going to happen. We just did not anticipate it would happen in 2.5 months.</p>

<p>After several busy weeks in Oct and Nov, we started preparing everything about two weeks ahead the trip: finding a place in SF, finding a subletter in Boston, renewing our plates and drivers license, planning a cross-country drive, moving our stuff to the storage, booking hotels and train tickets for the later china trip, goodbye dinners with boston friends, shipping our computers to a friend in the bay, and so many more. It felt a little insane at the beginning, but fortunately I have the best teammate.</p>

<p>“Crazy December” started on a cold morning shortly after Thanksgiving. We and our dog Toast squeezed into our 2005 Prius, packed with a robot, a 3D printer, GPUs, monitors, and one bag of clothes, and started our journey to the west. One week later, we were on a plane from SF to China. Two weeks after that, we drove to Portland to drop off Toast with Aaron’s mom, drove back the next day, and finally settled officially into SF on January 1, 2026.</p>

<p>As we drove on New Year’s Day, I remember telling Aaron that starting the year with a long drive probably said something about this year ahead: always moving.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Always moving]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding Deep Learning for Object Detection</title><link href="https://qiuyuchen14.github.io/blog/2018/redirect/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding Deep Learning for Object Detection" /><published>2018-06-04T17:39:00+00:00</published><updated>2018-06-04T17:39:00+00:00</updated><id>https://qiuyuchen14.github.io/blog/2018/redirect</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://qiuyuchen14.github.io/blog/2018/redirect/"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I will recover my old post from another server soon!]]></summary></entry></feed>